Field-Osgood Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Field-Osgood Family Papers 1702-1938 1780-1930
MSS83744
Field family
Osgood family
1,600 items
7 containers plus 3 oversize
7 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, speeches and writings, household financial accounts, legal papers, genealogical material, printed matter, photographs, lithographs, and engravings pertaining to the families of Samuel Osgood (1748-1813) and his daughter, Susan Osgood Field, of Massachusetts and New York.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bradhurst family.; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889--Correspondence.; Field family.; Field, Chloe.; Field, Hickson W. (Hickson Woolman), 1823- --Correspondence.; Field, Susan K. Osgood. Susan K. Osgood Field papers.; Field, William B. Osgood.; Osgood family.; Osgood, David, 1747-1822.; Osgood, Maria Bowne Franklin. Maria Bowne Franklin Osgood papers.; Osgood, Samuel, 1748-1813. Samuel Osgood papers.
Organizations
United States. Army. Signal Corps.; United States. Board of Treasury.; United States. Continental Congress.; United States. Postmaster General.; United States. War Department. Military Intelligence Division.
Subjects
Enslaved persons--Emancipation--New York (State); Sermons, American--18th century.; World War, 1914-1918--Photography.; World War, 1914-1918.; Young women--United States--19th century.
Places
Andover (Mass.)--Social life and customs.; Charleston (S.C,)--Social life and customs.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1775-1865.; Troy (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.
Titles
Field family papers; Osgood family papers
Acquisition Information
The Field-Osgood Family Papers were given to the Library of Congress by Diana Field from 1996 to 1998. The material was received jointly by the Manuscript Division and the Prints and Photographs Division. A group of Field-Osgood family pictorial material remains in the Prints and Photographs Division.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Field-Osgood family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The Field-Osgood Family Papers span the years 1702-1938, with the bulk of the material dating from about 1780 to 1930. The papers pertain to three ancestral families of the donor and are arranged in three sections: the Bradhurst family, the Field family, and the Osgood family, with the Field and Osgood papers forming the bulk of the collection. Many of the items were removed from deteriorating scrapbooks. With the exception of occasional items of a general nature concerning the family, the material is arranged alphabetically by individual family member. The papers include correspondence, financial material, legal documents, genealogical material, speeches and writings, printed matter, photographs, lithographs, and engravings.
Because so many individuals are represented in this collection, the topics touched upon are disparate and numerous. Of major importance are the papers of Samuel Osgood (1748-1813), member of the Continental Congress, one of the three members of the United States Board of Treasury (1785-1789), first postmaster general, and naval officer of the port of New York. A small amount of correspondence, writings, and Board of Treasury and port of New York documents are in the collection. Most of the Samuel Osgood material, however, relates to household financial matters. Additional household financial matter is found under his wife's name, Maria Bowne Franklin Osgood, including items concerning her financial obligations to Chloe Field, an African American woman. Also in the collection are four sermons of David Osgood (1747-1822), three printed and one holograph. One printed sermon of Joseph Lathrop (1731-1820) can be found in the folder for Thaddeus Osgood.
Samuel Osgood's daughter, Susan Kittridge Osgood Field, maintained a lively correspondence with her sisters, Martha Brandon Osgood, married and living near Troy, New York, and Juliana Osgood, married and living in or near Andover, Massachusetts. She also corresponded with Mary (a cousin?) living in Charleston, South Carolina. Nearly all of the letters date from 1814 to 1821, the year she married Moses Field. The letters from her sisters are full of descriptions and details of the everyday life of these young women. Susan Osgood Field's correspondence is filed with the Field family material.
Three items in the Field family papers merit notice: two eighteenth century manumission documents from New York state and a letter of 1845 from Robert Browning to Hickson Woolman Field. Also in the Field family papers are a collection of materials from the United States Signal Corps on aerial photography dating from 1917 to 1918 and a group of intelligence reports (circa 1918-1919) from the Military Intelligence Division of the War Department. Both groups of papers relate to William B. Osgood Field.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by name of family and alphabetically thereunder by name of person, topic, or type of material.
Container List
- Bradhurst family (Box 1)
  - Bradhurst, Samuel, appointment as ensign, eighty-second regiment, New York Infantry, 1828 See Oversize (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1750-1782, 1790, 1808, 1828, 1847, 1873, 1916, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1907-1910, undated See also Oversize (Box 1)
  - Poster, sale of Bradhurst estate as building lots, New York, N.Y., undated See Oversize (Box 1)
- Field family (Box 1)
  - Family trees, undated See also Oversize (Box 1)
  - Field, Anne, manumission papers for Pothena, 1777 (Box 1)
  - Field, Augusta, 1887-1892 (Box 1)
  - Field, Cyrus W., undated See also Oversize (Box 1)
  - Field, David Dudley, 1892, undated (Box 1)
  - Field, Eugene, 1892, undated (Box 1)
  - Field, Hickson Woolman (Box 1)
    - Browning, Robert, letter, 1845 (Box 1)
    - Miscellany, 1853, undated (Box 1)
  - Field, Lila Sloane, 1921, undated (Box 1)
  - Field, Maunsell B., 1850, 1869, 1874 (Box 1)
  - Field, May, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Field, Moses, 1817-1818 (Box 1)
  - Field, Osgood, 1848, 1876, 1914, undated (Box 1)
  - Field, Rodman, manumission papers for Elizabeth, 1782 (Box 1)
  - Field, Stephen J., 1890, undated (Box 1)
  - Field, Susan Osgood (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - 1814-1821, 1830-1834, (4 folders) (Box 1)
      - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Notebook, "Notes on the history of Rome," by Susan K. Osgood, and financial material and arithmetic notes by Walter F. Osgood, 1802-1821 (Box 2)
  - Field, William B. Osgood (Box 2)
    - Financial matter, 1929-1931 (Box 2)
    - Military appointments, orders, and notes, 1918-1924, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellany, 1902-1903, 1914-1928, undated (Box 2)
    - "Pedigree of William Bradhurst Osgood Field," 1909, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Poetry notebook, 1897-1898 (Box 2)
    - Printed matter re World War I, 1914-1918 (Box 3)
    - Travel journal, 1901 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Army Signal Corps (Box 3)
      - Aerial photography, 1917-1918, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
      - Lists of photographs (Box 3)
        - 1918, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - 1919 (Box 4)
    - War Department (Box 4)
      - Military Intelligence Division (Box 4)
        - Country reports, circa 1918, (7 folders) (Box 4)
        - General information, circa 1918, 1924, undated (Box 4)
        - Intelligence summaries, 1919 (Box 4)
      - News bureau, 1919 (Box 4)
  - Field, William H. (Box 5)
    - Journal of travel in Great Britain, 1850-1852 (Box 5)
    - Miscellany, 1857-1863, 1870-1883, 1891, 1915, undated (Box 5)
  - Field, William Osgood (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1922-1931, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. (Box 5)
      - Harvard Lampoon, 1924-1926, undated (Box 5)
      - Instrumental music clubs, 1923-1931, undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellany, 1922-1930, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Genealogical writings, 1868-1878 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous family members, 1702, 1796, 1806, 1832-1833, 1846, 1865, 1881, 1896-1916, 1924-1926, 1938, undated See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 6)
- Osgood family (Box 6)
  - Osgood, David (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1814 (Box 6)
    - Speeches and writings (Box 6)
      - "Dr. Osgood's sermon on the national fast, May 9, 1798," 1798 (Box 6)
      - Holograph sermon on I John, chapter 3, verse 2, 1816, 1821 (Box 6)
      - "Mr. Osgood's Thanksgiving sermon, December 11th 1783," 1783 (Box 6)
      - "A solemn protest against the late declaration of war," 1812 (Box 6)
  - Osgood, "Maria, "Miss," and "Mrs.," 1803-1814, undated (Box 6)
  - Osgood, Maria, to Chloe Field, 1810-1812 (Box 6)
  - Osgood, Samuel (1748-1813) (Box 6)
    - Biographical and pictorial material, 1931, undated (Box 6)
    - Board of Treasury, 1785-1789 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1775-1798, 1804-1808 (Box 6)
    - Financial matter, 1780-1781, 1800-1813, undated See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - Port of New York custom house, 1808-1809 See also Oversize (Box 6)
    - Speeches and writings (Box 6)
      - "A letter upon the subject of episcopacy" and response by "Philalethes," 1807 (Box 6)
      - Speech to the New York state assembly, 1801 (Box 6)
  - Osgood, Samuel (1784-1862), "The real and ideal in New England," undated (Box 6)
  - Osgood, Susan K. See Containers 1-2, Field, Susan Osgood (Box 6)
  - Osgood, Thaddeus, "Damnable heresies defined and described, in a sermon, preached in North Wilbraham; June 15, 1808, at the ordination of Rev. Thaddeus Osgood," by Joseph Lathrop, 1821 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous family members, 1731-1803, 1880, undated See also Oversize (Box 7)
  - Sloane, William Douglas, death of, 1915 (Box 7)
    - News clippings (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, (2 folders) (Box 7)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Bradhurst family (Box OV 1)
    - Bradhurst, Samuel, appointment as ensign, eighty-second regiment, New York Infantry, 1828 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
    - Poster, sale of Bradhurst estate as building lots, New York, N.Y., undated (Container 1) (Box OV 2)
  - Field family (Box OV 2)
    - Family trees, undated (Container 1) (Box OV 2)
    - Field, Cyrus, "Ocean Telegraph March," sheet music, cover only, with lithographic portrait, undated (Container 1) (Box OV 3)
    - Miscellaneous family members, document re land ownership, 1702 (Container 6) (Box OV 3)
  - Osgood family (Box OV 3)
    - Osgood, Samuel (1748-1813) (Box OV 3)
      - Financial matter, 1784-1805 (Container 6) (Box OV 3)
      - Port of New York custom house, certificate of ownership, 1809 (Container 6) (Box OV 3)
    - Miscellaneous family members, Isaac Osgood, Bunker Hill Memorial Association, undated (Container 7) (Box OV 3)